Do you know
هل تعلم
that we have 1.4 million cellular radio masts
انه لدينا 1.4 مليون هوائي من الراديو الخليوي
deployed worldwide?
موزعة حول العالم؟
And these are base stations.
وهذه هي المحطات الأساسية
And we also have
و ايضا لدينا
more than five billion
اكثر من 5 مليار
of these devices here.
من هذه الاجهزة هنا
These are cellular mobile phones.
هذه هي اجهزة هاتف خليوية متنقلة
And with these mobile phones,
ومع هذه الهواتف المتنقلة
we transmit more than 600 terabytes of data
نحن نرسل اكثر من 600 تيرابايت من البيانات
every month.
كل شهر
This is a 6 with 14 zeroes --
هذا 6 متبوعة ب14 صفر
a very large number.
رقم كبير جدا
And wireless communications
و الاتصالات اللاسلكية
has become a utility
اصبحت ذات منفعة عامة
like electricity and water.
مثل الكهرباء و الماء
We use it everyday. We use it in our everyday lives now --
نحن نستخدمها كل يوم,نحن نستخدمها في حياتنا اليومية
in our private lives, in our business lives.
في حياتنا الشخصية, في حياتنا العملية
And we even have to be asked sometimes, very kindly,
ونحن يجب ان نسأل في بعض الاحيان,بكل لطف
to switch off the mobile phone at events like this
ان نغلق الهاتف الجوال في احداث كهذه
for good reasons.
لاسباب مقنعة
And it's this importance
مدفوعاً بأهمية ذلك
why I decided to look into the issues
قررتُ ان ابحث في القضايا
that this technology has,
التي تواجه هذه التقنية
because it's so fundamental to our lives.
لانها اساسية جدا في حياتنا
And one of the issues is capacity.
و احد هذه القضايا هي السعة
The way we transmit wireless data is by using electromagnetic waves --
الطريقة التي نبث بها البيانات اللاسلكية هي باستخدام الموجات الكهرومغنطيسية
in particular, radio waves.
بالتحديد ,موجات الراديو
And radio waves are limited.
و موجات الراديو محدودة/قاصرة
They are scarce; they are expensive;
انها قليلة,انها مكلفة
and we only have a certain range of it.
و لدينا مجال محدد لها
And it's this limitation
وهذا التحديد/القصور
that doesn't cope
لا يتماشى
with the demand of wireless data transmissions
مع الطلب لبث البيانات اللاسلكية
and the number of bytes and data which are transmitted every month.
و عدد البايتات و البيانات التي يتم بثها كل شهر
And we are simply running out of spectrum.
و ببساطة ينفد منهم الطيف المطلوب
There's another problem.
هنالك مشكلة اخرى
That is efficiency.
وهي الكفاءة
These 1.4 million cellular radio masts, or base stations,
هذه ال1.4 مليون هوائي خليوي,او محطة اساسية
consume a lot of energy.
تستهلك الكثير من الطاقة
And mind you, most of the energy
و اغلب هذه الطاقة
is not used to transmit the radio waves,
لا تستخدم في بث موجات الراديو
it is used to cool the base stations.
انها تستخدم في تبريد المحطات الاساسية
Then the efficiency of such a base station
اذا الكفاءة لمثل هذه المحطات الاساسية
is only at about five percent.
فقط حوالي 5%
And that creates a big problem.
و هذه يخلق مشكلة كبيرة
Then there's another issue that you're all aware of.
و هنالك ايضا قضية اخرى كلكم مدركين لها
You have to switch off your mobile phone
يجب عليك اغلاق الهاتف
during flights.
خلال رحلات الطيران
In hospitals, they are security issues.
في المستشفيات,هنالك مشكلات امان
And security is another issue.
و الامان قضية اخرى
These radio waves penetrate through walls.
هذه الموجات تخترق الجدران
They can be intercepted,
يمكن اعتراضها
and somebody can make use of your network
و شخص ما يمكن ان يستغل شبكتك
if he has bad intentions.
اذا كان لديه نوايا سيئة
So these are the main four issues.
اذا هذه هي القضايا الاربعة الرئيسية
But on the other hand,
لكن من الناحية الاخرى
we have 14 billion of these:
لدينا 14 مليار من هذه
light bulbs, light.
مصابيح كهربية ,ضوئية
And light is part of the electromagnetic spectrum.
و الضوء هو جزء من الطيف الكهرومغنطيسي
So let's look at this in the context
اذا لننظر الى هذا في السياق
of the entire electromagnetic spectrum, where we have gamma rays.
من كل الطيف الكهرومغنطيسي حيث لدينا اشعة غاما
You don't want to get close to gamma rays, it could be dangerous.
لا تريد الاقتراب من اشعة غاما,قد تكون خطرة
X-rays, useful when you go to hospitals.
اشعة اكس,مفيدة عندما تذهب الى المستشفيات
Then there's ultraviolet light.
ثم هنالك الضوء الفوق البنفسجي
it's good for a nice suntan,
انه جيد لاكتساب سمرة لطيفة
but otherwise dangerous for the human body.
لكن غير ذلك خطر للجسم البشري
Infrared --
الاشعة تحت الحمراء
due to eye safety regulations,
ونسبة الى لوائح سلامة العين
can be only used with low power.
تستطيع فقط استخدامها مع طاقة منخفضة
And then we have the radio waves, they have the issues I've just mentioned.
وثم لدينا موجات الراديو, لديها القضايا التي ذكرتها للتو
And in the middle there, we have this visible light spectrum.
وفي الوسط هناك ,لدينا طيف الضوء المرئي هذا
It's light,
انه الضوء
and light has been around for many millions of years.
والضوء ظل موجودا لعدة ملايين من السنين
And in fact, it has created us,
وفي الواقع ,انه انشأنا
has created life,
انشأ الحياة
has created all the stuff of life.
انشأ كل الاشياء في الحياة
So it's inherently safe to use.
اذا هو بطبيعته آمن بالنسبة لنا
And wouldn't it be great to use that for wireless communications?
الن يكون من الرائع استخدام ذلك في الاتصالات اللاسلكية
Not only that, I compared [it to] the entire spectrum.
ليس ذلك فقط, لقد قارنته مع كل الطيف
I compared the radio waves spectrum --
قارنت طيف موجات الراديو
the size of it --
حجمها
with the size of the visible light spectrum.
مع حجم طيف الضوء المرئي
And guess what?
وخمن ماذا؟
We have 10,000 times more of that spectrum,
لدينا 10 الف ضعف من هذا الطيف
which is there for us to use.
الذي هو هناك لنا لاستخدامه
So not only do we have this huge amount of spectrum,
اذا ليس لدينا فقط هذا المقدار الكبير من الطيف
let's compare that with a number I've just mentioned.
فلنقارنها مع رقم ذكرته للتو
We have 1.4 million
لدينا 1.4 مليون
expensively deployed,
محطات راديو خليوية غير كفؤة
inefficient radio cellular base stations.
مركبة و موزعة بطريقة باهظة
And multiply that by 10,000,
و اضرب هذا العدد ب 10,000
then you end up at 14 billion.
يصبح لديك 14 مليار
14 billion is the number of light bulbs installed already.
14 مليار هو عدد المصابيح الكهربية المثبتة بالفعل
So we have the infrastructure there.
اذا لدينا البنية التحتية هناك
Look at the ceiling, you see all these light bulbs.
انظر الي السقف,انت ترى كل هذه المصابيح الكهربية
Go to the main floor, you see these light bulbs.
انظر الى المسرح الرئيسي انت ترى كل هذه المصابيح
Can we use them for communications?
هل باستطاعتنا استخدامها للاتصالات؟
Yes.
نعم
What do we need to do?
ماذا علينا ان نفعل؟
The one thing we need to do
الشيئ الوحيد الذي علينا فعله
is we have to replace these inefficient incandescent light bulbs,
انه يجب علينا استبدال هذه المصابيح الساطعة الغير فعالة
florescent lights,
مصابيح الفلورسنت
with this new technology of LED,
بهذه التقنية الجديدة من الثنائيات الباعثة للضوء
LED light bulbs.
مصابيح الثنائي
An LED is a semiconductor. It's an electronic device.
الثنائي هو شبه موصل,انه اداة الكترونية
And it has a very nice acute property.
وله خاصية لطيفة جدا
Its intensity can be modulated
يمكن تعديل حدته
at very high speeds,
بسرعة عالية جدا
and it can be switched off at very high speeds.
ويمكن تشغيله بسرعة عالية جدا
And this is a fundamental basic property
وهذه خاصية اساسية
that we exploit
التي استكشفناها
with our technology.
بتقنيتنا
So let's show how we do that.
اذا دعونا نعرض كيف نفعل ذلك
Let's go to the closest neighbor to the visible light spectrum --
لنذهب الى الجار الاقرب الي طيف الضوء المرئي
go to remote controls.
اذهب الى اجهزة التحكم عن بعد
You all know remote controls have an infrared LED --
كلكم تعلمون ان المتحكم عن بعد لديه ثنائي اشعة تحت الحمراء
basically you switch on the LED, and if it's off, you switch it off.
اساسا تشغل الثنائي,و اذا كان يعمل تطفئه
And it creates a simple, low-speed data stream
و يخلق دفق من البيانات بسيط منخفض السرعة
in 10,000 bits per second,
10,000 بت في الثانية
20,000 bits per second.
20,000 بت في الثانية
Not usable for a YouTube video.
لا يمكن استخدامها لفيديو اليوتيوب
What we have done
الذي فعلناه
is we have developed a technology
انه طورنا تقنية
with which we can furthermore
التي تمكننا
replace the remote control of our light bulb.
من استبدال جهاز التحكم عن بعد في مصابيحنا
We transmit with our technology,
نبث باستخدام تقنيتنا
not only a single data stream,
ليس فقط دفق بيانات واحد
we transmit thousands of data streams
نحن نبث الآلاف من تدفقات البيانات
in parallel,
بالتوازي
at even higher speeds.
بسرعة اعلى حتي
And the technology we have developed --
و التقنية التي طورناها
it's called SIM OFDM.
اسمها (SIM OFDM)
And it's spacial modulation --
و هي تعديل خاص
these are the only technical terms, I'm not going into details --
هذه فقط العبارات التقنية ,انا لن اخوض في التفاصيل
but this is how we enabled
لكن هكذا أستخدمنا
that light source
مصدر الضوء ذاك
to transmit data.
لبث البيانات
You will say, "Okay, this is nice --
سوف تقول "حسنا هذا جيد"
a slide created in 10 minutes."
شريحة تم إنشاؤها في 10 دقائق ".
But not only that.
لكن ليس ذلك فقط
What we've done
ما فعلناه
is we have also developed a demonstrator.
اننا ايضا طورنا موضِّح
And I'm showing for the first time in public
وانا اعرض هذا في العلن لاول مرة
this visible light demonstrator.
هذا موضِّح الضوء المرئي
And what we have here
وما لدينا هنا
is no ordinary desk lamp.
هو مصباح مكتب عادي
We fit in an LED light bulb,
نركب مصباح الثنائي
worth three U.S. dollars,
قيمته 3 دولارات امريكية
put in our signal processing technology.
نضع تقنية معالجة الاشارة الخاصة بنا
And then what we have here is a little hole.
وبعد ذلك ما لدينا هنا هو ثقب صغير
And the light goes through that hole.
و الضوء يدخل عبر ذلك الثقب
There's a receiver.
هنالك مستقبل
The receiver will convert these little, subtle changes in the amplitude
المستقبل سوف يحول هذه التغيرات الصغيرة و الطفيفة في المدى
that we create there
التي نوجدها هناك
into an electrical signal.
الى اشارة كهربية
And that signal is then converted back
و الاشارة الكهربية يتم تحويلها مرة اخرى
to a high-speed data stream.
الى دفق بيانات عالي السرعة
In the future we hope
في المستقبل نأمل
that we can integrate this little hole
اننا نستطيع أن ندمج هذا الثقب الصغير
into these smart phones.
في هذه الهواتف الذكية
And not only integrate a photo detector here,
وليس فقط ادماج كاشف ضوئي هنا
but maybe use the camera inside.
لكن ربما يمكن استخدام الكاميرا الموجودة بداخله
So what happens
اذا الذي يحدث
when I switch on that light?
عندما اشغل المصباح
As you would expect,
كما تتوقعون
it's a light, a desk lamp.
انه مصباح,مصباح مكتب
Put your book beneath it and you can read.
ضع كتابك اسفله وتستطيع القراءة
It's illuminating the space.
انه يضيئ المكان
But at the same time, you see this video coming up here.
لكن في نفس الوقت تستطيع ان ترى الفيديو هناك
And that's a video, a high-definition video
وهذا الفيديو فيديو عالي الجودة
that is transmitted through that light beam.
يتم بثه عن طريق شعاع الضوء
You're critical.
انتم ناقدون
You think, "Ha, ha, ha.
تفكرون "ها ها ها
This is a smart academic doing a little bit of tricks here."
هذا الاكاديمي الذكي يفعل بعض الخدع هناك"
But let me do this.
لكن دعوني افعل هذا
(Applause)
(تصفيق)
Once again.
مرة اخرى
Still don't believe?
مازلتم لا تصدقون؟
It is this light
انه هذا الضوء
that transmits this high-definition video in a split stream.
الذي يبث هذا الفيديو عالي التحديد
And if you look at the light,
واذا نظرت الى المصباح
it is illuminating as you would expect.
انه يضيئ كما تتوقع
You don't notice with your human eye.
لا تلاحظ بالعين البشرية
You don't notice the subtle changes in the amplitude
لا تلاحظ التغير الطفيف في المدى
that we impress onto this light bulb.
الذي نفرضه على هذا المصباح
It's serving the purpose of illumination,
انه يؤدي وظيفة الاضاءة
but at the same time, we are able to transmit this data.
لكن في نفس الوقت نستطيع بث هذه البيانات
And you see,
و تستطيع فقط ان ترى
even light from the ceiling comes down here to the receiver.
حتى الضوء من السقف يأتي لهذا المستقبل
It can ignore that constant light,
انه يستطيع تجاهل ذاك الضوء المتواصل
because all the receiver's interested in
لان كل ما يهم المستقبل
are subtle changes.
هو التغيرات الطفيفة
You also have a critical question now, and
لديكم ايضا سؤال نقدي بين الحين و الاخر
you say, "Okay,
انت تقول,"حسنا
do I have to have the light on all the time
هل يجب علي ابقاء الضوء مشتعلا طيلة الوقت
to have this working?"
ليكون هذا عاملا ؟"
And the answer is yes.
و الجواب هو نعم
But, you can dim down the light
لكن تستطيع تخفيض الضوء
to a level that it appears to be off.
الى درجة ان يظهر مغلق
And you are still able to transmit data -- that's possible.
و ما تزال بامكانك ان تبث البيانات ,ذلك ممكن
So I've mentioned to you the four challenges.
اذا لقد ذكرت لكم التحديات الأربع
Capacity:
السعة:
We have 10,000 times more spectrum,
لدينا 10,000 مرة طيف اكثر
10,000 times more LEDs
10,000 مرة ثنائيات اكثر
installed already in the infrastructure there.
مثبتة بالفعل في البنية التحتية
You would agree with me, hopefully,
ولعلكم تتفقون معي، كما آمل ،
there's no issue of capacity anymore.
ليس هنالك مشكلة سعة بعد الان
Efficiency:
الكفاءة:
This is data through illumination --
هذه بيانات عبر الاضاءة
it's first of all an illumination device.
هي في البداية اجهزة اضاءه
And if you do the energy budget,
و اذا قمت بحساب ميزانية الطاقة
the data transmission comes for free --
فإن بث البيانات يكون مجانيا
highly energy efficient.
كفاءة عالية في استخدام الطاقة
I don't mention the high energy efficiency
انا لم اذكر الكفاءة العالية في استخدام الطاقة
of these LED light bulbs.
لمصابيح الثنائيات هذه
If the whole world would deploy them,
اذا قام كل العالم بأستخدامهم
you would save hundreds of power plants.
ستوفر مئات من محطات الطاقة
That's aside.
بوضع هذا جانبا.
And then I've mentioned the availability.
و بعدها قمت بذكر الوفره
You will agree with me that we have lights in the hospital.
سوف تتفقون معي انه لدينا مصابيح في المستشفيات
You need to see what to do.
انت بحاجة لرؤية ما تفعله
You have lights in an aircraft.
لدينا مصابيح في الطائرات
So it's everywhere in a day there is light.
اذا انه في كل مكان يوجد ضوء
Look around. Everywhere. Look at your smart phone.
انظر حولك كل مكان,انظر الى هاتفك الذكي
It has a flashlight, an LED flashlight.
لديه ضوء فلاش ,ضوء فلاش مكون من ثنائي
These are potential sources for high-speed data transmission.
هذه هي مصادر محتملة لنقل بيانات بسرعة عالية
And then there's security.
وبعد ذلك هنالك الامان
You would agree with me
سوف تتفقون معي
that light doesn't penetrate through walls.
ان الضوء لا يخترق الجدران
So no one, if I have a light here,
اذا لا احد ,اذا كان لدي ضوء هنا
if I have secure data,
اذا كان لدي بيانات مؤمنة
no one on the other side of this room through that wall
لا احد في الجانب الاخر من هذه الغرفة عبر ذاك الجدار
would be able to read that data.
يستطيع قراءة تلك البيانات
And there's only data where there is light.
و هنالك فقط بيانات حيث يوجد ضوء
So if I don't want that receiver to receive the data,
اذا اذا لم ارد لذلك المُستقبل ان يستقبل البيانات
then what I could do,
ما استطيع فعله
turn it away.
توجيهه بعيدا
So the data goes in that direction, not there anymore.
اذا البيانات تذهب في ذلك الاتجاه ,ليس هناك بعد الان
Now we can in fact see where the data is going to.
الان في الواقع تستطيع ان نري الى اين تذهب البيانات
So for me,
اذا بالنسبة لي
the applications of it,
التطبيقات لها
to me, are beyond imagination at the moment.
بالنسبة لي, هي ابعد من الخيال في هذه اللحظة
We have had a century of very nice, smart application developers.
كان لدينا قرن زمني من مطوري تطبيقات الذكية اللطفاء جدا
And you only have to notice, where we have light,
ويجب عليك ان تلاحظ فقط ,حيث لدينا الضوء
there is a potential way to transmit data.
هنالك امكانية لبث البيانات
But I can give you a few examples.
لكن استطيع اعطائك بعض الامثلة
Well you may see the impact already now.
حسنا ربما ترى الاثر الان بالفعل
This is a remote operated vehicle
هذه مركبة مشغلة عن بعد
beneath the ocean.
تحت المحيطات
And they use light to illuminate space down there.
وهي تستخدم الضوء لاضاء المساحة هناك
And this light can be used to transmit wireless data
وهذا الضوء يمكن استخدامه لبث البيانات اللاسلكية
that these things [use] to communicate with each other.
ان هذه الاشياء تستخدمه للتواصل مع بعضها البعض.
Intrinsically safe environments
بيئة آمنة جوهريا
like this petrochemical plant --
مثل هذه المحطة البتروكيميائية
you can't use RF, it may generate antenna sparks,
لا تستطيع استخدام موجات الراديو ,انها قد تولد شرارة في الهوائي
but you can use light -- you see plenty of light there.
لكنها تستطيع استخدام الضوء ,انت ترى مصابيح كثيرة هناك
In hospitals,
في المستشفيات
for new medical instruments;
للاجهزة الطبية الحديثة
in streets for traffic control.
في الشوارع للتحكم في حركة المرور
Cars have LED-based headlights, LED-based back lights,
السيارت لها مصابيح امامية مبنية عل الثنائيات و كذلك مصابيح خلفية
and cars can communicate with each other
و السيارات تستطيع التواصل فيما بينها
and prevent accidents
و تمنع الحوادث
in the way that they exchange information.
بالطريقة التي يتبادلون بها المعلومات
Traffic lights can communicate to the car and so on.
اشارات المرور يمكن ان تتواصل مع السيارت و هلم جرا
And then you have these millions of street lamps
و بعد ذلك لديك هذه الملايين من مصابيح الشارع
deployed around the world.
موزعة حول العالم
And every street lamp could be a free access point.
وكل مصباح شارع سيكون نقطة وصول مجانية
We call it, in fact, a Li-Fi,
في الواقع نحن نسميه (Li-Fi)
light-fidelity.
دقة-الضوء
And then we have these aircraft cabins.
وثم لدينا كابينات الطائرات هذه
There are hundreds of lights in an aircraft cabin,
هنالك المئات من المصابيح في كابينة الطائرة
and each of these lights
وكل واحد من المصابيح
could be a potential transmitter of wireless data.
يمكن ان يكون مرسل محتمل للبيانات اللاسلكية
So you could enjoy your most favorite TED video
اذا يمكنك الاستمتاع بفيديو تيد المفضل لديك
on your long flight back home.
في رحلتك الطويلة الى المنزل
Online life. So that is a vision, I think, that is possible.
الحياة على الانترنت ,لذا انا اعتقد انه رؤية ممكنة
So, all we would need to do
اذا كل ما علينا فعله
is to fit a small microchip
هو وضع رقاقة صغيرة
to every potential illumination device.
لكل جهاز اضاءة محتمل
And this would then combine
وهذا سوف يتضمن
two basic functionalities:
وظيفتان اساسيتان
illumination and wireless data transmission.
الاضاءة وبث البيانات
And it's this symbiosis that I personally believe
وانه هذا التعايش الذي أعتقد شخصيا
could solve the four essential problems
يمكن ان يحل اربع مشاكل اساسية
that face us in wireless communication these days.
التي تواجهنا في الاتصالات اللاسلكية هذه الايام
And in the future,
وفي المستقبل
you would not only have 14 billion light bulbs,
لن يكون لدينا فقط 14 مليار مصباح كهربائي
you may have 14 billion Li-Fis
ربما يكون لديك 14 مليار (Li-Fi)
deployed worldwide --
موزعة حول العالم
for a cleaner, a greener,
لمستقبل انظف
and even a brighter future.
اخضر اكثر و مضيئ اكثر
Thank you.
شكرا لكم
(Applause)
(تصفيق)